<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>David Asboth - Data Solutions &amp; Consultancy - Data science</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/data-science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2022-11-21T13:54:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Why I now call myself a "data generalist"</title><link href="/why-i-now-call-myself-a-data-generalist.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-21T13:54:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-21T13:54:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-11-21:/why-i-now-call-myself-a-data-generalist.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've realised that pigeonholing myself as a data scientist, broad as that term is, doesn't work for me. Finding a good job title for myself is actually non-trivial. If you feel the same way, you may also be a "data generalist", and this post is for you.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm at an interesting crossroads in my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone asks me what I do, I say I'm a data scientist. That term is too broad, however; a few minutes on any job site will reveal that "data scientist" can mean someone with a PhD in molecular biology just as much as someone who builds robust data pipelines, all the way to someone who can use Excel quite well, and everything in between. We're fast approaching peak data science where everyone wants to be a data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This presents a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I keep saying I'm a data scientist, looking for work is a long and painful slog reading every single job description hoping that something suits me. As time goes on, I'm finding myself less and less excited about advertised data science roles. Something's been lost in the name. If I explicitly move away from calling myself that though, I miss out on a huge chunk of the market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sure I'm not alone in this. Data science attracts people from incredibly diverse backgrounds. There's no medical school for data science; we all have our own skills that we bring to the job. It shouldn't be a surprise if "data scientist" is therefore too broad to summarise us all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to work backwards. Start with my skill set and what I actually enjoy doing, settle on a specific job title later. Here's what I've done in my career to date:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've been paid to write code for over a decade. I can't imagine a future where I don't spend at least some percentage of my time writing code, but I also know I don't want to be a developer. I enjoy working with data, and people, and thinking about the big picture too much (not that developers don't do these, but it's not as typical).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've got over 5 years experience analysing, visualising, and presenting data, and building machine learning models. I love the former, ambivalent about the latter. I'm not an expert in statistics and I know I wouldn't want to specialise as a Machine Learning Engineer for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've also spent the last few years focused on designing and delivering data science/programming courses. Education is one of my real passions, maybe what I'm best at, but I am yearning to support this with technical work to keep my skills fresh and my life interesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I like building things. Specifically, quick proofs of concept and prototypes to help people decide whether something is a good idea or not, before they go too far down a path that delivers no value. This has been my favourite part of being a data scientist so far, even though it's not officially in the remit. I've "won" multiple company hackathons doing this, and I'd love to explore this skill further in my career.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my personal list, but all data scientists will have something similar. Maybe you have a specific bullet point for data modelling, which you've done and enjoyed, maybe it's the project management aspect that appeals to you. Perhaps you enjoy being the "translator" between technical teams. What we all have in common is a variety of past roles and technical/professional skills, a lot of which we learned on the job, and a desire to work with people and help them achieve their goals. We don't want to be fully technical and lock ourselves away from people, nor do we want to be in a purely non-technical role. Whatever axes you place jobs on, we're somewhere in the middle, and "data scientist" doesn't quite cut it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're generalists. Maybe that's it; we're data generalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Alan Hylands points out in this great post &lt;a href="https://alanhylands.com/generalists-real-data-science-unicorns"&gt;"Generalists Are The Real Data Science Unicorns"&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The further you go in your career, the likelihood will be that you will eventually gravitate more towards [becoming a specialist]. There will be an inevitable attraction (and aptitude) towards one aspect of the profession over the others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prevailing wisdom is that of specialisation. Job adverts expect to find specialists, bootcamps train specialists, and most discussion in the datasphere will be filed under "data science" or "data engineering" or "machine learning engineering" etc. Specialists are important. Often you want someone with deep expertise in one field. However, as we have talked about on the Half Stack Data Science podcast, data science in most organisations is messy and undefined, and that arena calls for generalists. Someone who can use their wide experience to solve problems on the fly, without necessarily being an expert in the tool they're using to solve the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After years of struggling to "find my niche" I'm now fully embracing the idea of being a T-shaped problem solver. A generalist. If what I've written here resonates with you, maybe you're a generalist too, and I'm here to tell you you're not alone, and you have a tribe. I have more to say on the practical side of being a generalist, but in the meantime here are some resources to get started:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The marvellous and aptly named &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/jonesrooy"&gt;Majoring in Everything podcast&lt;/a&gt; by Andrea Jones-Rooy. "A show for people who don't know what they want to do with their lives to explore the variety of kinds of lives out there with cool, smart people." - a generalist's dream.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The post "Generalists Are The Real Data Science Unicorns": &lt;a href="https://alanhylands.com/generalists-real-data-science-unicorns"&gt;https://alanhylands.com/generalists-real-data-science-unicorns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://counting.substack.com"&gt;Counting Stuff newsletter&lt;/a&gt; by self-proclaimed "die-hard generalist" Randy Au&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: if "data generalist" takes off, remember where you read it first :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Data science"></category><category term="featured"></category></entry><entry><title>Citizen Data Science</title><link href="/citizen-data-science.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-08T13:54:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-08T13:54:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-11-08:/citizen-data-science.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What does "citizen data science" mean beyond being a buzzword for "everyone should do data science" (which they most certainly shouldn't)?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Citizen Data Science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a popular phrase a few years back. At the peak of the data science hype cycle we somehow managed to go beyond "everyone needs data science" and start convincing ourselves that, in fact, everyone needs to be a data scientist. There was also a lot of pushback on this. After all, why should Debbie from Finance learn Python? Why should our salesmen be able to tell the difference between supervised and unsupervised learning? Clearly this was one step too far, or so we thought. At the time something bugged me about this particular debate, but I wasn't sure what. I agreed that data science should largely be restricted to its own function, not "democratised" just because it was becoming popular. My motivation wasn't gatekeeping, but a separation of concern. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I've since realised though is that some of the skills necessary for data science, namely the ones that make a data scientist a good analyst, are actually useful across the board. Much like how computer literacy is a necessary part of life in the 21st century, knowing a few data science fundamentals will only become more important. Specifically, there are two areas where I believe widespread education would be helpful: data literacy and an automation mindset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data literacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is data literacy exactly? There need not be a societal push to teach everyone confidence intervals and probability theory. You can be data literate without linear algebra. What most people need is an intuition to always be sceptical about data-driven findings, question every result, and put it in the wider context. Does this chart show what it claims to show? Do these reported numbers make sense, and if they seem plausible, is the process that generated them trustworthy and repeatable? Are there truly fewer Covid-19 cases over the weekend, or is it just that numbers aren't updated and reported until Monday?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All we need to do is let people flex this particular muscle. Discuss case studies, ones that contain realistic ambiguity. Most business decisions are made under uncertainty, regardless of the quality and quantity of data analysis. We need to better understand and embrace this. Data will not tell us what to do, it can only give us suggestions, and we need to be equipped to make the most of these. I argue this isn't a skill that only the biggest decision makers, the C-level execs need, this is something with which we should all get comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that's fine, our "citizens" don't need mathematical training, just an intuition for how to use data in the right way. But what about technical skills? How much programming for example do people need? Clearly not everyone needs to know how to train and deploy a machine learning model (although exposure to this process can't hurt, if only to help demystify it) but we also can't ignore the need for some technical training that people can genuinely benefit from. The balance is struck, in my opinion, when we focus on teaching programming for automation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Automation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automation is a superpower. If you have any sort of repetitive task that is part of your day-to-day, business as usual work, imagine how great it would be if the computer could do it for you. No, it wouldn't result in the computers taking away your job. I know people genuinely fear that, I get it. The right way to think about it is that automating the boring stuff (see the &lt;a href="https://automatetheboringstuff.com/"&gt;book/online course of the same name&lt;/a&gt;) frees you, the human, up to do the things that computers can't. Build human relationships. Consider nuance. See the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students of mine have already heard me on my soapbox about this. Learn just enough programming (Python or otherwise) to automate the boring stuff. The more practice you have with this skill, the more you will see it everywhere, and the smaller your tolerance will be for manually doing repetitive tasks. You should get annoyed that a stakeholder demands a particular report emailed to them every Monday. Find a way to take yourself out of the loop. Got a bunch of spreadsheets to download from different web pages and collate once a week? Write a script for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So what do we call this thing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's not call it "citizen data science", that sounds patronising to me. It probably doesn't even need a name (but then how will it ever go viral, David??). After the somewhat misguided idea of citizen data science came and went we're left with some key takeaways. There is a reason to take elements of data science beyond the data science team. We don't want any gatekeeping ("only data scientists should analyse data") and everyone benefits from data literacy and some basic coding knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Data science"></category><category term="featured"></category></entry><entry><title>How to use your impostor syndrome to learn anything</title><link href="/impostor-syndrome.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-08T13:54:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-08T13:54:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-11-08:/impostor-syndrome.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How can you harness your impostor syndrome? Get good at being able to learn anything.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;How to use your impostor syndrome to learn anything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a theory that data science is a field where impostor syndrome is particularly rife, more so than other fields. There is so much to know under the wide umbrella of "data science" that no single human can know it all, yet we all go around calling ourselves data scientists, so the implication is that we &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; know it all. The more you learn about what's out there, the easier it is to be overwhelmed that you couldn't possibly ever learn everything, and from there it's not a huge leap to "I will never be good enough". You might see a tweet or read a paper from a fellow data scientist working on a different part of the field and think it might as well be in a foreign language and your heart might sink that there's yet another thing you don't know yet. The truth is that it's perfectly normal and fine for people to specialise and therefore have different strengths, but we can't all see this clearly all the time, hence impostor syndrome proliferating among us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two ways to tackle impostor syndrome: either learn everything and genuinely don't be an impostor, or embrace the fact that you can't know everything at once, and instead get good at being able to learn anything. Clearly only one of those things works, and it's something of a slow-burning epiphany I've had over the years; I don't need to learn everything up front, I just need to be confident enough that I can learn anything when I need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to learn anything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside tackling impostor syndrome I've got my own reasons to want to know how to learn anything. As an educator I need to know how people learn, so I can teach them. As a data scientist, a career that itself requires a lifelong learning journey, I need to be able to figure out new concepts and algorithms pretty fast. As a consultant I also need to be able to teach myself new skills as they come up. When I was a software developer, I never wanted to pigeonhole myself as a "technology X developer", I'd have happily changed programming languages between jobs. Now as a data scientist, I don't even have a choice; every project is just so different. By this point I hopefully don't need to convince you that being able to learn something is a useful skill, but students often ask me how to "learn data science". That question itself is fraught with many rabbit holes, so rather than answering "well it depends on what you mean by data science" I usually give one piece of advice: learn by doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"David, that's so obvious, we hear that all the time" I hear you say. At least I hope some of you hear that advice every now and again. Obviously it makes sense to actually do the thing you're learning. Science even backs me up there - we retain more information if we apply our knowledge to a real life scenario. Not to digress here, but a big problem with the education system in many countries has always been too much rote memorisation, not enough application. This is also true of a lot of technical education, and especially counterproductive in data science, which is all about the application. Theories and equations will help you understand only a part of what makes data science a useful discipline. It took me years to learn this and even more years to apply it to how I approach the field. By now I've recognised in myself that the best way I learn something is to have a problem to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to hoard ebooks and links to free online courses with the (decidedly false) hope that one day I'd "get around to them". No points for guessing how many times I've sat down at my desk and thought "I should read one of those random ebooks or take one of those courses". The problem wasn't that I wasn't interested in the material; after all I'd saved the ebook for later. The problem was it wasn't immediately relevant, and that's where learning goes to die. If I don't have a clear example in my mind of where I'd use it, I won't be motivated to sit down and learn it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed a new approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning by doing means the problem should come first. I'm motivated to solve a particular problem, and only then do I ask myself what I need to know to solve it. Maybe I already know how to do it, maybe I need to read up on something I used to know about, or maybe I need to learn something from scratch. Either way, because there is a problem in front of me, I can be laser focused on learning just enough to get a satisfying answer. This means you learn a fraction of the thing you're using to solve the problem, and this used to terrify me. This sort of learning is a recipe for serious impostor syndrome. Yes, I've just used algorithm X to get to my answer, but don't ask me to derive the underlying equations or remember any of the commands I had to type to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revelation I had is that &lt;strong&gt;this is fine&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's fine to only know a small percentage of tool X, or algorithm Y. Just because you used it once, doesn't mean you should hold yourself to an expert standard. Clearly you're not an expert at it yet, just someone who managed to work out how to use it for your problem, but the problem was the goal and you got there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly to "learn by doing" you need to do lots of that "doing" thing. My advice to students is always to work on little pet projects. They'll help hone your skills, learn new ones, and make a portfolio to show prospective employers. You'd be surprised how few people take me up on that advice (myself included, I'll admit). Maybe because it's only one part of the equation. It's fine to "do stuff" but what if the feeling of impostor syndrome won't go away?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it doesn't need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Channel your inner impostor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impostor syndrome is a reminder that you don't know everything, but it could also be a reminder that you &lt;em&gt;can't&lt;/em&gt; know everything. In fact, being an impostor is not a bad mindset for a data scientist trying to make sense of the business around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One mindset shift I recommend for data science is that you should always be the stupidest person in the room, or on a Zoom call I guess. When someone talks about basic concepts, company metrics like conversion, churn, or even "customer", you should always ask for a definition. You might feel it risks singling you out as someone who "doesn't know", but you'd be surprised how hard it is to get a consistent definition for concepts that people talk about all the time. We shouldn't be afraid to question basic assumptions; in fact, progress often lies there. Think of it like a reverse impostor syndrome: by freeing yourself from the weight of knowing everything, you boldly go into a meeting as someone who is ignorant but eager to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously this goes for non-technical topics. You should probably always be the one in the room who knows the most about, say, linear regression, but if you've just been hired at an agricultural firm as a data scientist and know nothing about agriculture, don't be afraid of that fact. Use it to your advantage. The same way anxiety can be a good thing before an important speech or meeting, because it shows you care enough about doing well to be anxious, impostor syndrome can also be a useful companion. Free yourself and ask all the questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's hear it for impostor syndrome. We only ever talk about it as if it's a disease plaguing our industry, but it can also be our secret weapon in getting things done. Don't worry about learning it all up front. You'll almost always be measured on what you achieve, not what you know. I like the framing "just in time" learning rather than "just in case". In the meantime, just go and do stuff. Stuff that interests you, without worrying about what you'll learn from it or whether you'll learn anything. Chances are you'll learn along the way and be better equipped next time. And think of your self-imposed "impostor" label not as a judgement, but an opportunity to always learn something new.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Data science"></category><category term="featured"></category></entry><entry><title>How to Connect to Google Sheets in Python</title><link href="/connecting-to-google-sheets-in-python.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-13T13:54:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-13T13:54:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-11-13:/connecting-to-google-sheets-in-python.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A quick tutorial on how to connect to Google Sheets in Python, so you can access it like a regular CSV file.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In most data science and machine learning tutorials you typically
encounter csv files. Either you connect to them locally, something like
this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pandas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;read_csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;my_local_data.csv&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you access them via a direct url like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pandas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;read_csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;http://www.lotsofdata.com/hosted_data.csv&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I rarely see though is connecting to slightly more obscure data
sources. You will probably end up doing this once you go out into the
real world of data science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One useful data source is Google Sheets. If you have a spreadsheet
hosted on Google Drive, which is made available for public access, and
want to access it, it's not immediately clear how to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's go through an example of how to connect to one. I'll use a
spreadsheet that has the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/17Mr201gfDoOTe5ONLS6LYJi1wQbtT26srXeSwUjMK0A/htmlview?usp=sharing&amp;amp;sle=true"&gt;Hacker News salary survey results&lt;/a&gt;
from a couple of years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can't use the url directly, because the url isn't just pointing to
the data, it's pointing to the entire Google Sheets interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead you need the sheet's export link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this simply take the url until the /d/ part, and the unique ID
that comes after, so this much:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/17Mr201gfDoOTe5ONLS6LYJi1wQbtT26srXeSwUjMK0A"&gt;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/17Mr201gfDoOTe5ONLS6LYJi1wQbtT26srXeSwUjMK0A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and add &lt;strong&gt;/export&lt;/strong&gt; at the end with some parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can specify the sheet number (zero-indexed) using &lt;strong&gt;gid&lt;/strong&gt;, and the
format to be csv using &lt;strong&gt;format&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full url then becomes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/17Mr201gfDoOTe5ONLS6LYJi1wQbtT26srXeSwUjMK0A/export?gid=0&amp;amp;format=csv"&gt;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/17Mr201gfDoOTe5ONLS6LYJi1wQbtT26srXeSwUjMK0A/&lt;strong&gt;export?gid=0&amp;amp;format=csv&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try that in your browser and it will download the csv file directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can then read it into pandas and it will be treated as a regular csv
file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the &lt;a href="https://github.com/davidasboth/blog-notebooks/blob/master/connecting-to-google-sheets/Connecting%20to%20a%20Google%20Sheet.ipynb"&gt;associated Jupyter notebook&lt;/a&gt;
to see it all in action.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Data science"></category><category term="featured"></category></entry></feed>