<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>David Asboth | Data Science - self improvement</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/self-improvement.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-11-30T19:03:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Lessons Learned from Blogging for 30 Days</title><link href="/blog/30-day-blog-challenge-complete" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-30T19:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-30T19:03:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-11-30:/blog/30-day-blog-challenge-complete</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I did it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote 30 blog posts in 30 days (including this one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm including this one because I wanted to look back at what I got out
of this little experiment in the hopes that it will be useful to others,
so I intend this post to be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I did it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote 30 blog posts in 30 days (including this one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm including this one because I wanted to look back at what I got out
of this little experiment in the hopes that it will be useful to others,
so I intend this post to be a useful edition to my blog rather than some
sort of self-backpatting (not a real word).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Positives&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the positives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;They turned out OK&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did this little experiment in the spirit of NaNoWriMo, where people
write a 50,000+ word novel in a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know that if I dedicated an entire month to nothing but writing
and managed a 50,000+ word novel, it wouldn't be good. It feels like a
goal so unrealistic that I'd lose the motivation very soon and write
rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was worried that this logic would carry over to this project; that
after 30 days I'd be so fed up of writing blog posts that they'd start
turning out terribly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd like to think that there wasn't a visible drop in quality over the
30 days. I mean, I managed to write them all in full sentences, stayed
on-topic, and didn't resort to rambling about random subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I have 30 more blog posts than I started with&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously this was the entire purpose of the exercise, but because I
feel they turned out OK, I have 30 more &lt;strong&gt;usable&lt;/strong&gt; blog posts than I
started with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At my previous pace it would have taken me decades to generate this much
content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;No time to overthink&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a daily deadline really got rid of all the distractions and
self-doubt that plagued my blogging efforts before. I had no time to
think about whether a topic was worth discussing - if it was related,
and I felt I could write something useful about it, it was good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Good enough" is a concept I'm better friends with now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Putting yourself out there&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tweeted about every blog post to make sure I was keeping myself
honest. It created a habit that helped me focus on getting the next post
written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Negatives&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously things weren't all rosy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Make it STOP!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a &lt;strong&gt;long&lt;/strong&gt; month. Having even an hour commitment each evening
was hard work sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being an adult is hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do I even have 30 ideas?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not going to lie, there were some days I struggled to think of what
to write about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had maybe 7-8 topics I knew I wanted to write about beforehand, and a
few small machine learning tutorials I wanted to write up, but the other
two thirds of the time the posts were conceived on the day or the day
before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to do this for another 30 days I might simply run out of
ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Big topics, small posts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I had the opposite problem. I thought of a good topic to
tackle, but due to the time pressure probably didn't do it justice. Or I
responded to a piece of news, such as &lt;a href="/blog/all-your-web-data-are-belong-to-us/"&gt;the UK's IP bill&lt;/a&gt;,
but would have liked to write a more complete, well-researched view of
it. I actually &lt;a href="/blog/more-on-the-snoopers-charter/"&gt;did that with the IP bill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion and Advice to Future Bloggers (or past me)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, doing something like this forced me out of my comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a whole month I regularly had to create content and put it out there
without the level of scrutiny and deliberation I normally would have
subjected it to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now more comfortable with my posts being good &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; instead of
always aiming for 'perfection'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realised I had lots of code snippets, Jupyter notebooks, and
half-finished machine learning tutorials lying around that I never got
around to writing up. Now they're out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually enjoy writing and, apart from a few days where I wished I
didn't have this task looming over me, I'm glad I've been writing so
much recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The momentum is with me, although I will almost certainly stop producing
daily posts (I also have another writing challenge to finish in the near
future, in the form of a Master's thesis). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my advice to anyone reading this, including a past version of me,
would be to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/just-do-stuff/"&gt;do it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're struggling to add to your blog/portfolio, want a boost to help
you complete half-finished code projects, or you want to get over your
insistence on perfection (I'm looking at you, past me), start a similar
challenge!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't have to be a whole month, start with less if you want. As
I've alluded to before, starting is almost certainly always the hardest
part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get you going, here's some text that you can copy-and-paste into a
tweet to announce your challenge to the world. Fill in the gaps where
appropriate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm starting a blogging challenge: ___ posts in ___ days. My
first topic will be ____, watch this space!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As silly and patronising as this might appear, the "secret" is to reduce
the barrier to entry, to remove obstacles. I've reduced it now to almost
just Ctrl+C, Ctrl+V. No excuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once that tweet is out there, you'd be surprised at how much focus and
discipline you can muster to make sure you actually complete your
challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's to more blogging!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="self improvement"></category><category term="featured"></category></entry><entry><title>Getting Started</title><link href="/blog/getting-started" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-16T19:58:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-16T19:58:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-11-16:/blog/getting-started</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Following on from &lt;a href="/blog/just-do-stuff/"&gt;yesterday's post&lt;/a&gt; about getting
stuff done I want to address what I think is the hardest part about it:
getting started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That may sound obvious, so let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Starting is Hard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on my observations, I'm more likely to sit down and work on a side …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Following on from &lt;a href="/blog/just-do-stuff/"&gt;yesterday's post&lt;/a&gt; about getting
stuff done I want to address what I think is the hardest part about it:
getting started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That may sound obvious, so let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Starting is Hard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on my observations, I'm more likely to sit down and work on a side
project or blog post if I've already got something to work on. That's
either something that I started previously, or just an idea that's been
bouncing around my head long enough for me to want to act on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm also typically unlikely to cut my work short once I've started it.
Programming is a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)"&gt;flow&lt;/a&gt;
activity and, unlike say &lt;em&gt;doing your taxes&lt;/em&gt;, once you get started it's
rare to feel like stopping after 10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means if you're like me, the hardest part is the initial hurdle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting started.
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Starting is Hard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons why it takes considerable effort to sit down and
start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Fear of Wasting Time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ties in with the point about it being easier to continue working on
something than starting something completely new. I often worry about
how productively I'm spending my free time. If I start working on
Project X, that will mean I'm not progressing with Project Y and working
on Project Z would also be a good use of my time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this does is stop me from working on any of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;"I Don't Have Any Free Time"&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest lie we tell ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are obviously days or weeks when it's true, but isn't it funny how
I can &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; find time for another Netflix episode?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Too Many Ideas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A variant of previous points, but it's worth mentioning that sometimes
you just can't decide which of your ideas to work on, only to give up
working on any of them. Yes it sounds like a laughable excuse, but we're
all great at fooling ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Perfectionism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of my favourite posts on the topic of procrastination, David Cain
talks about perfectionism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a procrastinator of my kind, perfection (or something negligibly
close to it) thereby becomes the only result that allows one to be
comfortable with him&lt;em&gt;self&lt;/em&gt;. A procrastinator becomes
disproportionately motivated by the pain of failure.
&lt;small&gt;From: &lt;a href="http://www.raptitude.com/2011/05/procrastination-is-not-laziness"&gt;Procrastination Is Not Laziness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is especially true of work that you will inevitably share somehow,
be it on a blog or Github, or just by showing it to your friends. If
you're a certain kind of person, this can be a very powerful deterrent
indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Impostor Syndrome&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related to the above. If you are too concerned with how good your work
is compared to everyone else's (especially that of experts in the field)
you can end up convincing yourself that there's no point even starting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tips on Getting Started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I realise that all sounds insurmountable. I've found that the key is
to use these mind games to your advantage and effectively try to trick
yourself into starting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on my own experience I have some suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Artificial Deadlines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, pressure can be a good thing. With side projects, there's
rarely any pressure to get things done, so creating an artificial
deadline for yourself is a good way to focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That begs the question of how you avoid procrastinating over this new
artificial deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My suggestion for that is to &lt;strong&gt;externalise&lt;/strong&gt; the pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell a friend that you're working on Project X and you'd like to show it
to them next Tuesday. Or tweet about it, saying a blog post is coming on
Friday. It's critical that you set a specific time for this, otherwise
you can keep pushing it back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By doing this, you're making yourself accountable to &lt;em&gt;other people.&lt;/em&gt;
Sure there's probably no consequence if you miss the deadline, but it
might still be enough to help you push through the first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're also putting your future self in a situation where &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; doing
stuff is the worse outcome, because you'd have to go through the shame
of going back on your word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cheap trick, but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Unrealistic Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might sound odd, but actually aiming higher than what you think is
reasonable could help get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been putting off writing on my blog for months. Then one evening I
thought "I know, I'll write 30 blog posts in 30 days". Bear in mind that
previously I'd barely written one every 2-3 months! It was a hugely
ambitious mini-project considering my track record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly it was clear that to make this work I'd have to ensure I have
enough time every day to write a blog post. That's on average an hour a
day I'd have to commit to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly though, it gave me a focus I never had when I was just
casually contemplating writing my next post. There was no time to second
guess myself because I had no more than an hour a day to get something
done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was &lt;em&gt;almost easy&lt;/em&gt; to sit down and get cracking because there was
literally no time to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also made use of my other trick of external pressure by immediately
tweeting about it. Then there was no going back, and I'm already halfway
through a content-creating marathon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for that, Past Me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Rousing Speech&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know how in films there's often a point where a character says a
rousing speech and everyone around them just goes "yeah, let's do
this!"?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, it was this one: &lt;a href="http://www.cracked.com/blog/6-harsh-truths-that-will-make-you-better-person/"&gt;6 Harsh Truths That Will Make You a Better Person&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever feel you're struggling with getting stuff done, read that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it will make you go "yeah, let's do stuff!".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Be Forgiving&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I said at the end of my previous post, it's important not to take
failure too seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don't have to be productive all the time. In fact, we're probably too
obsessed with it. I know I can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take it too seriously, procrastination can cause a lot of
distress and productivity becomes a burden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So sometimes, choose &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to do stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just make sure it's a choice you're actively making, not an excuse to
procrastinate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnote: This was the 16&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; entry in my &lt;a href="/blog/30-posts-in-30-days/"&gt;30 day blog challenge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="self improvement"></category><category term="featured"></category></entry><entry><title>Just Do Stuff</title><link href="/blog/just-do-stuff" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-15T16:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-15T16:44:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-11-15:/blog/just-do-stuff</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I read an article called &lt;a href="https://medium.com/&amp;64;bgilham/making-time-for-side-projects-22fbee546b45#.8f9myvkmq"&gt;Making Time for Side Projects&lt;/a&gt;
and its associated &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12949469"&gt;Hacker News discussion&lt;/a&gt;. It got me
thinking about all the advice I've read over the years about
productivity, about how best to use your time, and how to stop
procrastinating over side projects and just get …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I read an article called &lt;a href="https://medium.com/&amp;64;bgilham/making-time-for-side-projects-22fbee546b45#.8f9myvkmq"&gt;Making Time for Side Projects&lt;/a&gt;
and its associated &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12949469"&gt;Hacker News discussion&lt;/a&gt;. It got me
thinking about all the advice I've read over the years about
productivity, about how best to use your time, and how to stop
procrastinating over side projects and just get stuff done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know the answer to how you get stuff done; I'm still just slowly
getting used to spending more time &lt;em&gt;actually doing things&lt;/em&gt;. I've written
&lt;a href="/blog/procrastination-and-monkeys/"&gt;about procrastination&lt;/a&gt;
before, and I'll likely return to this topic every now and again. Partly
so that I can reread it later in case I forget what I've learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I'm just going to share the random thoughts I've had after reading
that article. Which brings me onto my first point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Too Much Reading, Not Enough Doing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was one comment in particular from that HN thread that caught my
eye and motivated this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder how many hours that would have otherwise been productive
have been spent reading about productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the tongue-in-cheek tone, there's a lot of truth there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've fallen into this trap many times - you read an insightful post,
learn some home truths, get some clarity, and understand your situation
better. You feel like something's clicked and you'll never look at the
problem of procrastination the same way again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you just go back to &lt;em&gt;not doing stuff&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What "stuff"?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point I want to clarify something. The problem I'm describing is
related to procrastinating over things &lt;em&gt;no one is making you do&lt;/em&gt;. Maybe
that's why it's hard, because you're not accountable to anyone, but I'm
strictly only talking about working on these side projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can easily get through life and have a decent career without
spending time outside of work bettering yourself. You'll probably miss
out on opportunities to meet people or learn things, but side projects
are not essential in the way that, say, &lt;em&gt;going to work&lt;/em&gt; is. Again, maybe
that's why it's easy to procrastinate over it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unsolicited Advice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realise the irony of talking about this problem when I've just said
that reading about it is one of the barriers to getting stuff done. I'm
afraid the only advice that I can offer is, in my view, the only
universally "good" advice on the subject:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter what it is. Write a blog, learn a new framework, mess
around with automating something on your computer, scrape a random
website for data. Anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overthinking and overcomplicating are the enemies of getting things
done. For bigger projects, obviously make a plan but if you're ever
stuck or feel overwhelmed that your side project is big, or you're not
sure how to continue, just &lt;em&gt;do stuff&lt;/em&gt;. Don't think about how it will fit
into the bigger picture. Don't think about how good a portfolio piece it
will be. Just do stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been following this maxim for about a year now, with what I thought
was almost no success. When I decided to do this &lt;a href="/blog/30-posts-in-30-days/"&gt;30-day blogging challenge&lt;/a&gt; and
had to get a list of ideas together to get started, that's when I
realised how many almost-finished side projects I had. None of them were
very big, but they were all the result of me just sitting down and
&lt;em&gt;doing something&lt;/em&gt;. The structured nature of this challenge and the tight
daily deadline finally brought me enough focus to start finishing them
off by polishing the code and writing up blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly I started producing content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stop Consuming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bigger picture version of the "too much reading" idea is one of the
harsh truths pointed out in the Making Time for Side Projects article
(and others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is that you should &lt;strong&gt;stop consuming&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;start creating&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite articles on the subject, which I will talk about in
more depth in a later post, says this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You hate yourself because you don't do anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harsh, but true. At least in my case it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final Musings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realise this all can come across as a bit preachy. Perhaps it is less
so if I point out that I fail at this &lt;em&gt;all the time&lt;/em&gt;. This entire piece
is mostly just aimed at a past version of me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I've come to understand is that yes, these points are all true;
it's obviously better to do things than not do things. But you also have
to understand that you will fail. You will sometimes inevitably spend a
whole Sunday playing video games instead of working on stuff. We're all
human after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that happens, just forgive yourself and move on. We don't have to be
"productive" all the time (I'll return to that idea).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're halfway through that Sunday and catch yourself
procrastinating, then take some time and &lt;em&gt;do stuff&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnote: This is the 15&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; entry in my &lt;a href="/blog/30-posts-in-30-days/"&gt;30 day blog challenge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="self improvement"></category><category term="featured"></category></entry><entry><title>Other People</title><link href="/blog/other-people" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-02T18:11:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-02T18:11:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-11-02:/blog/other-people</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you were applying for a new job and had a choice between working on a
project alone or with other people, which would you choose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introverts might prefer a project where they minimise human interaction,
and some people really do work better if they're left alone for long
periods …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you were applying for a new job and had a choice between working on a
project alone or with other people, which would you choose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introverts might prefer a project where they minimise human interaction,
and some people really do work better if they're left alone for long
periods of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not one of those people. I do my best work with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Working with Others&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I wanted to start moving from web development to data science, I
could have spent my free time doing various online courses to learn the
material, working on side projects to sharpen my skills and eventually
getting good enough to apply for jobs. However, that would have involved
me doing most of it alone. Without the ability to exchange ideas with
people, get feedback on my work and get that feeling of "we're in this
together" I wouldn't have made enough progress. In the end I bit the
bullet and enrolled on a Master's programme, and it was the right
decision (for me).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benefits of collaborating with others is probably higher in data
science than other professions, because it's often so exploratory in
nature. Even in software engineering it's plausible to be the only
developer on a project and still create a perfectly good product. I'd
speculate that the gains in adding a second data scientist to your team,
though, are much higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might be wrong, and there will almost certainly be amazing data
scientists out there who are working on their own and wouldn't gain much
from a second team member, but my feeling is they're the minority.
Certainly you need to work with other, non-technical people from the
business to make sure you're solving the right problems and in the right
way, so you can't be completely in isolation anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Others Outside of Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about outside of work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm quite an extroverted person and I'm probably not alone in feeling
energised by the presence of like-minded people who are motivated by the
same things, e.g. data science. Hit Reply, a podcast I listen to,
dedicated &lt;a href="https://hitreply.co/ep/6/surround-yourself/"&gt;an entire episode&lt;/a&gt; to the benefits of
surrounding yourself with others if you're a startup founder, or just
working on a side project with the view to making it into a startup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can feel myself being a lot more motivated to work on a side project
even if I just talk about it for a bit with other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you're like me, what can &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; do to be around the right kind of
"other people"?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Meetups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meetup scene in London is particularly big and diverse. You wouldn't
have to go too much outside of your interests to find a meetup to attend
&lt;em&gt;every single day&lt;/em&gt;. Just searching for the word "data" on
&lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/"&gt;meetup.com&lt;/a&gt; gives me a list where I could
easily pick a daily meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often joke that if you want to save money on food, go to a meetup that
has free pizza every night. On top of getting dinner for free you'll
also learn loads and meet new people!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You shouldn't do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Online Communities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you want to be part of a community without being physically
present. Maybe you want to watch from the sidelines as people talk about
topics of interest, or you just don't have the time to attend meetups
all the time. Online communities are a great alternative. Just off the
top of my head, you'll find plenty of content and discussion on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://reddit.com/"&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; (e.g.
    &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MachineLearning/"&gt;/r/machinelearning&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://quora.com/"&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/"&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stats.stackexchange.com/"&gt;"Cross-Validated" on Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these are more geared towards general discussion, some are Q&amp;amp;A
sites, but they're all communities where you can be surrounded
(virtually) by the right kind of people. Being part of a Slack channel
also helps - we (MSc students) use ours regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you do to be surrounded by the right people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnote: This was the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; entry in my &lt;a href="/blog/30-posts-in-30-days/"&gt;30 day blog challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="self improvement"></category></entry><entry><title>The Power of Podcasts</title><link href="/blog/the-power-of-podcasts" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-01T21:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-01T21:12:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-11-01:/blog/the-power-of-podcasts</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been thinking about podcasts recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spend a significant amount of my week doing necessary things that feel
like lost time, like commuting or washing the dishes. When I commute I
usually have my phone out, probably playing a pointless game just to
pass the time. When I do …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been thinking about podcasts recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spend a significant amount of my week doing necessary things that feel
like lost time, like commuting or washing the dishes. When I commute I
usually have my phone out, probably playing a pointless game just to
pass the time. When I do the dishes I feel like "the dishes being done"
is not enough of a return on the investment of time that I put in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These pockets of time are perfect for listening to podcasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general I feel like it's probably worthwhile putting my attention
into what I'm doing rather than letting my mind wander, but in these
cases I make a conscious decision to put my attention elsewhere. I want
to hear about new ideas, keep up with the latest technology news or
machine learning research, and if I can do it while I'm doing something
that needs to be done anyway, I feel like I'm &lt;em&gt;winning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also find podcasts a good tool for learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone learns differently, but I find I retain more information that I
&lt;em&gt;hear&lt;/em&gt; than I read. I only have limited time to dedicate to learning new
things, so again podcasts seem like the right kind of resource. It also
helps that there are some great podcasts out there for data science and
technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to share a few of the podcasts I listen to, specifically for
those interested in data science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Data Science Podcasts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://dataskeptic.com/"&gt;Data Skeptic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like Data Skeptic because of the way they alternate between episodes
dedicated to single concepts in data science, and interesting
interviews. Recommended both from a learning perspective, and for the
inspiration of hearing people talk about their cool projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://partiallyderivative.com/"&gt;Partially Derivative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lighthearted (but sometimes serious) alternative to the more
learning-heavy podcasts out there. The hosts are entertaining and
alternate between talking about data news to talking to interesting data
people. This is definitely the most "beginner-friendly" podcast on the
list because it's more about the data &lt;em&gt;stories&lt;/em&gt; rather than the
technical details. I like it because it adds variety to a list that's
otherwise quite technical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.becomingadatascientist.com/category/podcast/"&gt;Becoming a Data Scientist Podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Host Renee Teate documents her path to becoming a data scientist,
interviewing plenty of inspiring data science people along the way. The
podcast is accompanied by an excellent &lt;a href="http://www.becomingadatascientist.com/learningclub/"&gt;learning club&lt;/a&gt; for aspiring
data scientists. I was a contributor for a while and a guest on &lt;a href="http://www.becomingadatascientist.com/2016/06/15/becoming-a-data-scientist-podcast-episode-12-data-science-learning-club-members/"&gt;one of the episodes&lt;/a&gt;,
but that's not why you should check it out. Also season 2 is coming
soon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.thetalkingmachines.com/"&gt;Talking Machines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguably the most advanced and technical data science/machine learning
podcast out there. The hosts interview academics, including machine
learning greats Geoff Hinton and Yann LeCun, and discuss advanced topics
in machine learning. This one is harder to listen to while doing the
dishes because it requires my full attention, but it's always useful and
educational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://talkpython.fm/"&gt;Talk Python to Me&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not limited to data science, this one is all about Python. I've only
recently started listening to it, and already I've heard gems like &lt;a href="https://talkpython.fm/episodes/show/77/20-python-libraries-you-aren-t-using-but-should"&gt;20 Python Libraries You Aren't Using But Should.&lt;/a&gt;
Recommended for all Python programmers and anyone interested in the
Python ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Other Podcasts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://hitreply.co/"&gt;Hit Reply&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recently-launched podcasts about startups. The hosts have experience
launching software products and each episode is dedicated to advice on a
different matter, like competition or productivity. I'm enjoying it so
far!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://youarenotsosmart.com/podcast/"&gt;You Are Not So Smart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"A celebration of self delusion", this one's all about human behaviour,
hidden biases, logical fallacies, that kind of thing. The podcast also
contains &lt;a href="https://youarenotsosmart.com/cookie-recipes/"&gt;cookies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What podcasts do you listen to? I'm always looking for recommendations! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnote: This was the first entry in my &lt;a href="http://davidasboth.com/2016/11/01/30-posts-in-30-days/"&gt;30 day blog challenge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="self improvement"></category></entry><entry><title>30 Posts in 30 Days</title><link href="/blog/30-posts-in-30-days" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-01T19:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-01T19:24:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-11-01:/blog/30-posts-in-30-days</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today marks the start of November. That's usually not particularly
interesting, but November happens to be &lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org/"&gt;National Novel Writing Month&lt;/a&gt; (or NaNoWriMo for short - just rolls of
the tongue). The idea behind NaNoWriMo is simple;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"&lt;em&gt;writing a 50,000-word novel by 11:59 PM on November 30&lt;/em&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today marks the start of November. That's usually not particularly
interesting, but November happens to be &lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org/"&gt;National Novel Writing Month&lt;/a&gt; (or NaNoWriMo for short - just rolls of
the tongue). The idea behind NaNoWriMo is simple;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"&lt;em&gt;writing a 50,000-word novel by 11:59 PM on November 30&lt;/em&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, there's a geekier version: &lt;a href="https://github.com/NaNoGenMo/2016"&gt;National Novel &lt;em&gt;Generation&lt;/em&gt; Month&lt;/a&gt;, where the goal is to write
code that writes a 50,000 word novel. That's the only constraint - a
minimum of 50,000 words. There have been some hilarious entries over the
years, but I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why am I bringing up NaNoWriMo? At this point you might be half
expecting me to announce that I'll participate and write a novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me quash that idea right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the spirit of NaNoWriMo I've decided to set myself a
challenge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write 30 blog posts in 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I like writing -  I need a way to get into the habit of writing
    more, although it's entirely possible I'll hate writing by the end
    of the month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've always wanted to maintain a blog - Well, more accurately, I've
    always wanted to &lt;em&gt;be someone who maintains a blog&lt;/em&gt;. I just never got
    around to the part where you actually do it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to experiment with what it's like to release content which I
    don't have too much time to curate. In the past I've been known to
    spend hours on a single blog post agonising over tiny details in
    pursuit of "perfection" - this needs to stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, I currently have a Master's thesis due in 2 months, so
    spending a whole month writing thousands of words towards a
    different thing somehow sounds like a good idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ironically it's also an experiment in &lt;em&gt;beating&lt;/em&gt; procrastination.
External pressure can be helpful in forcing you to do stuff - &lt;a href="http://waitbutwhy.com/2013/11/how-to-beat-procrastination.html"&gt;as Tim Urban puts it&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re trying to write a consistent blog, put “new post every Tuesday” at the top of the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Rules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;30 posts in 30 days, although not strictly one per day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This post doesn't count.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Err, that's it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll try and create a mix of small technical write-ups, targeted lists
of resources and general musings about software, data, machine learning,
AI and technology and life in general. I will try to make each post
meaningful so I don't feel like I'm cheating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll also &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/davidasboth"&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; about each blog post
as I write them. If you want to attempt a similar thing (even just 5
blog posts in 30 days) let me know!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="self improvement"></category></entry><entry><title>Procrastination and Monkeys</title><link href="/blog/procrastination-and-monkeys" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-03-12T13:58:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-03-12T13:58:00+00:00</updated><author><name>david</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-03-12:/blog/procrastination-and-monkeys</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Procrastination has always affected me as a tech professional. You can
probably tell by the fact that this is my first blog post for a few
months. Ideas have been brewing, but I never got around to writing them
up. Not spending your time on side projects, blogs, learning new …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Procrastination has always affected me as a tech professional. You can
probably tell by the fact that this is my first blog post for a few
months. Ideas have been brewing, but I never got around to writing them
up. Not spending your time on side projects, blogs, learning new things
etc. can be harmful both to your career and your mental health, so it's
a topic worth exploring. I've spent a lot of time over the years reading
about it and wanted to share some of what I've read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is a short reading list for those interested in the topic of
procrastination, and it follows on from a talk I gave at the excellent
&lt;a href="https://mkgeeknight.co.uk/"&gt;MK Geek Night&lt;/a&gt;. Here is the
&lt;a href="https://soundcloud.com/mkgn/mkgn-16-david-asboth-procrastination-and-monkeys"&gt;audio&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/secret/A9UhRGl7sWTqfH"&gt;accompanying slides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're reading this while you should be doing something else, I hope
you appreciate the irony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Articles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://waitbutwhy.com/2013/10/why-procrastinators-procrastinate.html"&gt;Why Procrastinators Procrastinate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you only read one thing from this list, it should be this. It's the
daddy of all procrastination literature, and chiefly where the idea of
procrastination linked to monkeys came from. The whole blog is
fantastic, sadly also a great source of things to read when
procrastinating...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.raptitude.com/2011/05/procrastination-is-not-laziness/"&gt;Procrastination is not Laziness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A post from &lt;a href="http://www.raptitude.com/"&gt;Raptitude&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favourite
blogs. Reading this particular post was a real eye-opener, and it's what
started me on my journey of trying to understand procrastination. It
gave me a lot of insight into the procrastinating behaviour and really
hit home. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Books&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Now Habit&lt;/em&gt; - Neil Fiore&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A classic book in the procrastination literature. David Cain mentions it
in his Raptitude post, and I can only echo that a lot of it resonated
with me too. Fiore's idea of an "Unschedule" is a particularly good
thing to try. Disclaimer: no monkeys in this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Chimp Paradox&lt;/em&gt; - Prof Steve Peters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not chiefly about procrastination, the whole book is centred on
the "inner chimp" and what to do about it. The insights are definitely
applicable to procrastinators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;War of Art&lt;/em&gt; - Steven Pressfield&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A book with short, sharp chapters dealing with Resistance, Pressfield's
personification of procrastination. Again, no monkeys, just some real
home truths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Hacker News Threads&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10267564"&gt;"The cure for procrastination? Forgive yourself"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10156240"&gt;"To Stop Procrastinating, Start by Understanding the Emotions Involved"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I've bookmarked a couple of threads from Hacker News.
Procrastination comes up quite often, as it's a topic that affects a lot
of us in the tech industry, and I found it immensely helpful to see
other people's perspectives. The underlying articles are good too, but
it's the discussion that I think makes these particularly worthwhile
reading. It's great to read a well-written article or book on the
subject, but sometimes it helps to hear it directly from those affected
by it, in a less edited, 'raw' form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just a small slice of what's out there on the subject of
procrastination, and I'd welcome some of your suggestions on resources
that I haven't included but you feel are worth sharing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="self improvement"></category><category term="featured"></category></entry></feed>